"Centrum Multivitamin, Vitamin C, Beta Carotene,
Souvenaid, Zinc, or Calcium Supplements
to Prevent Alzheimer's"
Alzheimer's patients have
significantly lower blood levels
of 8 out of 10 antioxidants
investigated,
though, of course,
this could just be a consequence
of demented individuals
eating diets
poor in fruits and vegetables.
When put to the test,
the PREADViSE study
found no benefit
for vitamin E or selenium
in terms of
preventing dementia.
What about other antioxidants?
In the Harvard Physician's
Health Study,
nearly 6,000 older men
were randomized
to beta carotene or placebo.
No difference was found
after three years,
but after 11 years,
those unknowingly taking
the equivalent
of 3/4 cup (150 g)
of sweet potato
worth of beta carotene a day
had slightly
yet significantly better
overall cognitive performance.
A similar study of older women
found no cognitive benefit
over a period of nine years.
Maybe they just didn't wait
long enough?
Vitamin E and C
were also tested.
Vitamin E similarly flopped
throughout and so did vitamin C,
up until the last cognitive
assessment at around year 9
where the vitamin C group
appeared to pull ahead.
However, two trials of
a combination of vitamin C, E,
and beta carotene together
versus placebo,
one randomizing
1,500 older patients
for seven years,
and another truly massive one
randomizing more than
20,000 adults for five years,
both failed to show
any cognitive benefit
for the antioxidant cocktail.
What about a multivitamin?
The Physician's Health Study
also tested
taking the daily
multivitamin/multimineral
supplement Centrum Silver
for 12 years.
Compared to those instead
randomized to a placebo,
the Centrum group experienced
no cognitive benefit.
Souvenaid is a nutritional drink
containing a patented
formulation of nutrients,
branded as Fortasyn Connect,
specifically designed to help
in Alzheimer's disease.
Unfortunately,
it doesn't work.
There have been three
randomized controlled trials
enrolling more
than a thousand people,
and those taking Souvenaid
were no less likely
to develop dementia
in the first place,
and probably it has
little or no effect
on measures of memory
or other thinking skills
in both those
with mild cognitive impairment
or Alzheimer's disease.
In terms of specific minerals
other than the failed selenium,
zinc has similarly flopped
to improve overall cognition
over months or years
of supplementation,
and it's possible
calcium supplements
could make things worse.
Cross-sectionally,
those taking calcium
have more "hyperintensity"
brain lesions on MRI
(shown here in red, denoting
evidence of mini-strokes)
and longitudinally over time,
women taking
calcium supplements
appear to have twice the odds
of developing dementia.
The Women's Health Initiative
should have been able
to settle the question
once and for all.
Thousands of older women
were randomized
to calcium supplements
(plus vitamin D)
or placebo
for about eight years.
Thankfully, there was
no difference in the risk
of developing cognitive
impairment or dementia.
But that's what
was originally found
for heart attack
and stroke rates
before pre-existing
supplement use
was taken into account.
See, more than half of the women
were already taking
personal calcium supplements
before entering the study
and being randomized
to calcium or placebo.
You can imagine how this
could muddy the results.
If you just look at the women
who weren't
on calcium beforehand,
starting calcium resulted
in a significant increase
in the risk
of cardiovascular events,
consistent with a meta-analysis
of calcium trials
showing a 15 percent increase
in heart attacks or strokes
among those randomized
to calcium supplements
over placebo.
Unfortunately,
such a reanalysis
has yet to be performed
on the dementia data.
The bottom line is that vitamin
and mineral supplements
probably aren't going to help
prevent dementia or treat it,
but there are tons
of other things we can do.
Preserving your Mind
is the largest chapter
of my book How Not to Age.
Check it out
at your local public library
or listen to me read it
on audiobook.
All proceeds I receive
from the sales of all my books
go to charity.